Okay, here we go. How about this one? Any good? This one?
I like this one. This one goes on and do it. Sorry, I'm dithering.
This is a video all about how you take a full color image like this and turn it into a purely black and white image.
None of this gray scale ridiculousness. And a while ago I did a video which was like self-referential
text where the text would describe how many pixels are in that image of the text.
and there was a deleted scene about what happens when you go all white or all black using a threshold.
So let's go full black and white.
What we can do is just pick some threshold and above that level of gray we go
by the white and below it we go black and that's what the slider over here is indicating.
I mean that's not part of the frame I'm putting that on afterwards.
In fact the count up here for the number of black pixels and white pixels not part of the image
although spoiler, that's where we're going.
The idea with the shot was to demonstrate the difference
between black and white, like real black and white,
and what people call black and white.
There's actually grayscale,
and I had a lot of fun put the code together,
we rented that, and then we cut it.
Because you know, sometimes you put a lot of effort in
for the luxury of cutting it out of the edit,
and it was already a very full video.
A video I love underperformed on YouTube,
what are you gonna do?
I liked making it.
And so we took that scene out,
but it always kind of stuck with me.
I was like, you know what, there is something in that.
How do you take an image and make it pure, black or white
and keep as much information as possible?
We can try it on this shot as well.
So here it is.
Okay, if you did naive 50% threshold,
it looks like this.
Super dark, you can still kind of make me out,
but we've lost basically everything from the background
and the classic log perception of darkness, I guess,
because if we got to 75% it looks like this.
It's just, it's just, the lamp is the only thing
that survives at 75%.
And this is 25%.
So now the bottom 25% of brightness
from zero to 255 goes down to black,
everything else goes to white.
You get some detail on my face.
There's a little bit up over there,
but we're losing a lot there.
My head is just banishing into the wall.
I played around for a while.
This specific shot, I think 35% is the best threshold.
that's keeping a decent amount of detail here.
You can still kind of see the football's not bad,
but like look how severe the shadow is.
And this thing, it looks like there's an object there.
That's just the shadow of this.
The point is if you're trying to get detail
and you've only got black or white
and a single threshold where you're rounding one way or the other,
very hard to keep like fine detail
and darker detail, all that kind of jazz.
And it gets even worse,
where we to go somewhere that's much more visually interesting.
Such as this, there's some detail.
Now we think the best threshold for this scene is 28.
That's what you're looking at right now.
Everything below 28% brightness is going to black,
the bulb is going to white.
It's the best we could do to kind of keep the detail
in the front of the church over there
and you can still see some detail in my face,
but the top of my head is indistinguishable from the sky.
The fire has gone on the church.
To get that back, we tried a threshold of 40 there.
There's better, but now we've lost so much other details.
So we think 28 is the best.
However, what if we weren't applying the same threshold
to every pixel, but we mix it up a little?
And the result looks like this.
Okay, so there's a lot of static noise going on,
but there's definitely more detail.
And check it out, you can see me
and you can see the spire.
And you can see basically everything.
So somehow by applying randomness,
we've put noise into the shot,
we've managed to preserve more detail.
So compare this to when we had the 28 threshold,
the best from before.
So over on this side, let's say, random noise.
Over here, 28 threshold.
Huh?
Look at this, terrible.
Different type of terrible.
Other actually, we moved the camera around.
So the spire goes in and out.
You can see that, you know, we're able to keep that separate
from the sky by using randomness,
and we can't do that with a threshold,
at least without losing everything else.
So what's the deal with random noise giving us detail
back into our black and white image?
Well, first of all, I just wanna tell you one thing
you don't actually need to know.
If we zoom right in on this image down to the pixel level,
these individual pixels are actually little groups
of four by four pixels.
because what I did, I scaled everything down to one K
because we filmed at 4K, I go to a quarter of the resolution,
then I do all the processing, the black and whiteing,
and then we pop it back out again to 4K
and we do that with a kind of hard edge nearest neighbor.
Technique, which means what look like pixels
are actually little four by four groups of pixels.
But if I did this with true pixels in 4K,
by the time we're done, if you're watching it on an HDTV,
you're watching it on a phone,
it would all just blur together.
So that's why the two pixels aren't real pixels,
but you should better see them.
You need to know, but I just thought it'd be fun to share.
Speaking of things you need to know,
you need to know this video sponsored by Jane Street,
because their Academy of Math and Programming
is now accepting applications.
More about that at the end of the video
in the description below.
Let's talk about the noise.
What the random thresholds are achieving
is taking some of the pixels in light regions
and pushing them dark when they shouldn't be
and taking some pixels in the dark regions
and pushing them light.
And that's happening random or rather proportional
to how far from being light or dark each pixel is.
And what that's doing is giving us, well, shades of gray.
Because if you had to come up with gray scale coloring
from scratch using only black and white,
you'd put together like a palette of grays like this
where you've got more or fewer black pixels in each one.
So as you kind of lean back and blur your eyes,
They become different amounts of gray.
And what the random thresholds are doing
is basically this,
but in an ad hoc fashion.
Because the brighter or darker a region is,
the moral fewer pixels get pushed in the wrong direction.
So we're basically hitting all these
in between combinations.
The only issue is random noise is, of course,
doing that randomly.
If only there was another way,
we could do it systematically.
New location,
where we're gonna try a new filter,
which looks like this, it's not bad.
I mean my head a little bit disappears into that building,
but we're keeping like, look at the detail
on the hanging basket.
And the background is not bad,
but it does have that weird kind of old school newspaper feel
and that's because it's based on a repeating pattern.
Any dithering scheme that uses repeated pattern,
like what we just saw, is called ordered dithering.
Specifically, I was using a 2x2 Bayer-ordered dithering,
which gives you five different shades of gray.
Well, you get all white and all black,
and then you get three in the middle
where you color in one, two, or three black pixels.
And that's it, that's your whole spectrum.
That kinda works.
You just take that, have it as a repeating tile
over the entire size of your image,
and then use that as your series of filters.
And the way you can get it to gradually step up
you just set them as different thresholds and it works.
But the point is they turn on in that order.
But what if we don't want just a two by two repeating pattern?
Oh, well, you can go so much better.
In fact, Bayer dithering works for any two to the end
by two to the end grid.
Allow me to demonstrate.
The secret as such to Bayer dithering
is the order in which the pixels flip from black to white
or vice versa.
And they fire off in a very specific order
as an area gets brighter and brighter.
The first one to go is the top left,
that one there flips first, that's picks number one.
As we get brighter, then number two fires,
then number three,
and finally we fill it in with number four.
You might be thinking for a two by two grade,
there's not a lot of ways to do it differently.
But if you ever think about it, you could do it wrong.
If you fired one and then two underneath,
the moment you go up into a slightly brighter shade of gray,
you get weird vertical lines appearing.
And you don't want vertical horizontal lines,
which is why we go diagonal
and then a corner and then the other diagonal
by staggering the order in which we go from white to black
or black to white.
You are less likely to get weird patterns.
And it's better when you look at it with your human eyeballs
and you kind of average it out into a gray.
Things get more complicated though
when we go to a bigger grid size.
Bayer dithering works for any two to the end grid.
So you can basically double it each time to get the next one up.
And what you do is you imagine this as being
like four lots of the previous ones.
There's one there, another one there, another one there.
And then you do the same pattern recursively
as you scale it up.
So of these subgrids, you always do them in that order.
This one, then that one, then that one, then that one.
And then within each one, you do them in this order.
So for example, we're gonna do top left for all of them first
in this order.
we do top left there, one, top left there, two, and then three, and then four. And now
we come down to here and we do them in this order. So there's five, six, seven, eight.
Now we're going to do that one in all of them in that order. So that's now nine, ten,
11, 12 and finally 13, 14, 15, 16.
And you could repeat this and do an 8 by 8,
or a 16 by 16 and so on.
It's a fantastic little recursive algorithm.
And if you turn the pixels on and off in this order,
you get a fantastic range of shades of gray.
But what would that look like?
Back out in the real world.
Welcome back to the scene from before.
we're still in the 2x2 Bayer filter
and just take a little note of what you can and can't see.
And ready?
Here's the 4x4.
Isn't that special?
You can see these bricks.
Ready?
Okay, back to 2x2.
They gone.
4x4, they're back.
You can see all the brickwork over here.
Look at the background and my face.
In fact, if we do, we'll do a split screen
as soon as this car comes through.
You ought to do it now.
I'm over here.
This is the 2x2 side
where that car is just driven through.
Ah, look at the emotion you can see now.
And if you're thinking, well hang on,
if the 4x4 is this good, imagine the 8x8.
But here's the 8x8.
It's the same.
Here's 16.
Above a point, it doesn't make a big difference.
So for this scene at the resolution,
we're using the 4x4, what a winner.
So there's your two options.
Use completely random thresholds
and get a nice organic look,
but maybe not as many nice separations
of grays as we would like.
Or you use something ordered like Bayer Dithering,
you get loads of nice distinct grays,
but you get a weird repeating newspaper-esque lock.
Are you only two options of a fraud?
It's not like there's some fantastic third option
in the middle, with the best of both.
Of course there is.
It's called blue noise.
Instead of using pure random noise,
you can use blue noise and you get much better grays.
And here's blue noise out in the wild.
You don't even know what this scene looks like.
All you can see is this dithered version,
but it's not bad.
Look at the posts.
The posts like you can see they get darker as you go back.
You can almost make out there's like brickwork and tiles.
Just have a look at what detail you can get.
We can also compare this to pure random.
Actually, we can do our split screen again.
So I'm blue, blue noise on this side,
random noise on this side, or come with me,
round over here, past producing a call with the bounce,
because it makes so much difference
once we've did it the shot.
There's a tree, there you go.
Blue noise and random noise.
You be the judge.
Right, we all love blue noise,
but what actually is it?
And how does it differ from true random noise?
If we were to extract our random thresholds
for every pixel and just visualize them
going from white to black, it would look like this.
There you go.
It's just standard random noise.
Blue noise looks like this subtly different.
So in the true random, your brain is doing human brain things.
It's looking for patterns.
You might be spotting some threads or filaments in there
because real random noise clumps.
Like you're gonna have hotspots and cold spots
at every different scale, whereas blue random noise.
That's a lot more like, it was like remember when,
well some of you might remember when the iPod shuffle came out
and it was true random and everyone got upset
because they're occasionally here
the same song twice in a row.
Yes, because that's randomness.
you get every possible string and arrangement
in there somewhere, including things repeating,
which is why you get like bright spots and dark spots.
All people wanted was a shuffle,
and blue noise is much closer to being a shuffle.
You don't just put things in randomly,
you make sure, on average, they're all roughly evenly spaced.
It's nicely distributed noise.
And you can see that if we blur them both,
because if we blur blue noise on a small,
like let's say five pixel radius,
it goes totally gray, whereas true noise,
you can still see hotspots and cold spots.
There's still some structure in there
because white noise has structure
at every frequency, it's white, it's called white noise,
whereas blue noise only has variation
on very small distances.
High frequency, like blue.
You also get different color, audio noise,
not going near that.
I'm pretty sure it's the same thing,
but the point is this is not pseudo-random,
but it's not true random, it's blue random
and it looks a lot better.
There's some blue noise, amazing.
It's just incredible detail,
but you don't get a repeating pattern.
And the reason you get the best of both worlds
is it is still pretty random,
but also it has that same property of Bayer dithering
whereas the pixels turn on,
the order in which they turn on
is very evenly distributed.
So if I take this blue noise
and I cycle it all away from completely black
to completely white and see when the different parts of the filter turn on and,
guess, turn off, you'll see at the extremes it's just a bunch of points fairly evenly distributed,
but yet randomish.
In fact, if we pause it there, if you talk about humans, arrange themselves in a room randomly
that end up standing a bit like this because humans would think random means evenly distributed,
but a bit offset.
It's not a grid.
And that's exactly what we get here.
Blue noise is what humans think true noise is,
but it's not, it's blue noise.
If you're thinking, come on Matt,
what about the dithering system you came up with?
Well, who has to think I'm gonna come up with a course I did
and we'll talk about that in a moment,
but first I wanna thank the sponsor of this video,
Jane Street, because their AMP course
is accepting applications now.
AMP is Jane Streets' Academy of Math and Programming.
It's for recent high school graduates
who had some kind of barrier to their education,
but they wanted pursue an education in math or computer science.
AMP runs from the very end of June,
right through to the very end of July, 2026.
And over that month, the curriculum
will focus on solving problems,
involving things like mathematics, computer programming,
game theory, and much more.
Not only will Jane Streets cover your travel to New York City,
accommodation, your food, and all fees associated with the costs.
But if you make it onto AMP, they will also give you a $5,000 scholarship to help you
further your education.
To apply for AMP, you don't need any particular background in finance or coding.
You just need to be intellectually curious and have a love of mathematics and computer
science.
The deadline for applying for AMP, if you are a high school student or you know a high school
student and you can pass us on to them, is the 11th of March.
So get onto it, it's a huge amount of fun.
I go every year so you get to see me,
I'm in Ezra Perk, I just love solving the sorts of puzzles
that they have at app.
In fact, they gave me one recently
that I could ever go at.
Imagine you're in a three game tennis competition
where to be the champion, you have to win two consecutive games.
Your opponents are Jenny, the best tennis player in the club,
and Carla, who is less good.
You either have to play Jenny, Carla, Jenny,
or Carla, Jenny, Carla.
your non-tennis challenges, which way around would give you the greatest probability of winning
two consecutive games?
I like this puzzle because there is kind of an intuitive way to look at it, but also
you can just work it out.
Which I did.
Here's all my working.
I had a lot of fun doing it.
I hope seeing this really clears things up.
All the puzzle details will also be in the description if you want to try.
As will the details for applying to AMP.
Thank you so much.
I mean, I know this is not for everyone, but if you are that high school student or you
you know someone who is, this could be a life-changing opportunity.
So please do spread the word.
Huge thanks to Jane Street for not only running AMP,
but also sponsoring this video.
And now for my dithering technique,
because I first came across all of this
and got obsessed by it when I watched a bunch of YouTube videos
about the mass behind the video game,
return of the Obradin.
And in that game, everything is black and white-didded.
Although within each shot, there's different types of dithering
and you move around in 3D but the dithering works.
It's just incredible.
I will link to the videos I watch below
if you wanna check them out, but just got me thinking,
oh, you can come up with different types of dithering.
In fact, they use new types of dithering
for that video game.
So I was like, well, I'm gonna do my own.
But what could I possibly base Parker dithering on?
Well, I thought what about the original Parker thing?
I used to Parker Square.
I used a three by three grid where that's 29%,
1%, 47%, et cetera, thresholds.
Now, is that a good way to do it?
No.
In fact, I'm now Parker Dithered.
And you see, so the issue is,
because we got some 1%ers here,
they're like always white,
because what's gonna get below 1%,
so you always get this, if you zoom in,
these little pair of diagonal pixels,
it's just always on.
But I think that adds a certain amount of fun texture to a scene.
And it works outside as well.
Check it out, there's the tree from before.
That's not a bad amount of detail.
If you come over here,
other side of producers Nicole again.
You can feel of this.
There's your tiles up there.
We've got the posts from before.
That guy walking through?
It's not bad.
Even this shot isn't bad with the Parker filter, huh?
We've got the spire.
And I think that weird texture,
nice moody element on the graveyard.
And while we're here, thank you for visiting my Myspace page.